Chapter 10. a bosom friend.
Returning to the Spouter Inn from the chapel, I found Quiqu there quite alone,
he having left the chapel before the benediction some time. He was sitting on
a bench before the fire with his feet on the stove hearth, and in one hand was
holding close to his face that little negro idol of his, peering hard into its
face, and with a jack knife gently whittling away at its nose, meanwhile
humming to himself in his heathenish way. But being now interrupted, he put
up the image, and pretty soon, going to the table, took up a large book there,
and placing it on his lap, began counting the pages with deliberate
regularity, at every 50th page, as I fancied, stopping a moment, looking
vacantly around him, and giving utterance to a longdrawn, gurgling
whistle of astonishment. He would then begin again at the next 50, seeming to
commence at the number one each time, as though he could not count more than 50,
and it was only by such a large number of 50s being found together, that his
astonishment at the multitude of pages was excited. With much interest I sat
watching him, savage though he was, and hideously marred about the face, at
least to my taste, his countenance yet had something in it which was by no
means disagreeable. You cannot hide the soul. Through all his unearly
tattooings, I thought I saw the traces of a simple, honest heart, and in his
large, deep eyes, fiery black and bold, there seemed tokens of a spirit that
would dare a thousand devils. And besides all this, there was a certain
lofty bearing about the pagan, which even his uncoutheness could not
altogether maim. He looked like a man who had never cringed, and had never had
a creditor. Whether it was too that his head being shaved, his forehead was
drawn out in freer and brighter relief, and looked more expansive than it
otherwise would. This I will not venture to decide, but certain it was. His head
was frenologically an excellent one. It may seem ridiculous, but it reminded me
of General Washington's head, as seen in the popular busts of him. It had the
same long, regularly graded, retreating slope from above the brows, which were
likewise very projecting like two long promonitories thickly wooded on top.
Quiquake was George Washington, cannibalistically developed.
Whilst I was thus closely scanning him, half pretending, meanwhile, to be
looking out at the storm from the casement, he never heeded my presence,
never troubled himself with so much as a single glance, but appeared wholly
occupied with counting the pages of the marvelous book. Considering how sociably
we had been sleeping together the night previous, and especially considering the
affectionate arm I had found thrown over me waking in the morning, I thought this
indifference of his very strange. But savages are strange beings. At times you
do not know exactly how to take them. At first they are overawing. Their calm
self-clectiveness of simplicity seems a socratic wisdom. I had noticed also that
Quiquake never consorted at all or but very little with the other seaman in the
inn. He made no advances whatever appeared to have no desire to enlarge
the circle of his acquaintances. All this struck me as mighty singular. Yet
upon second thoughts, there was something almost sublime in it. Here was
a man some 20,000 mi from home by way of
Cape Horn, that is, which was the only way he could get there, thrown among
people as strange to him as though he were in the planet Jupiter. And yet he
seemed entirely at his ease, preserving the utmost serenity, content with his
own companionship, always equal to himself. Surely this was a touch of fine
philosophy, though no doubt he had never heard there was such a thing as that.
But perhaps to be true philosophers, we mortals should not be conscious of so
living or so striving. So soon as I hear that such and such a man gives himself
out for a philosopher, I conclude that like the dispic old woman, he must have
broken his digesttor.
As I sat there in that now lonely room, the fire burning low in that mild stage,
when after its first intensity has warmed the air, it then only glows to be
looked at, the evening shades and phantoms gathering round the casements,
and peering in upon us silent solitary twain, the storm booming without in
solemn swells. I began to be sensible of strange feelings. I felt a melting in
me. No more my splintered heart and maddened hand were turned against the
wolfish world. This soothing savage had redeemed it. There he sat, his very
indifference speaking a nature in which there lurked no civilized hypocrisies
and bland deceits. Wild he was a very sight of sights to see. Yet I began to
feel myself mysteriously drawn towards him. And those same things that would
have repelled most others, they were the very magnets that thus drew me. I'll try
a pagan friend, thought I, since Christian kindness has proved but hollow
courtesy. I drew my bench near him, and made some friendly signs and hints,
doing my best to talk with him.
Meanwhile, at first he little noticed these advances, but presently upon my
referring to his last night's hospitalities, he made out to ask me
whether we were again to be bedfellows.
I told him yes, where I thought he looked pleased, perhaps a little
complimented. We then turned over the book together, and I endeavored to
explain to him the purpose of the printing and the meaning of the few
pictures that were in it. Thus I soon engaged his interest, and from that we
went to jabbering the best we could about the various outer sightes to be
seen in this famous town. Soon I proposed a social smoke, and producing
his pouch and tomahawk, he quietly offered me a puff, and then we sat
exchanging puffs from that wild pipe of his, and keeping it regularly passing between us.
If there yet lurked any ice of indifference toward me in the pagan's
breast, this pleasant, genial smoke we had soon thawed it out, and left us
cronies. He seemed to take to me quite as naturally and unbiddenly as I to him,
and when our smoke was over, he pressed his forehead against mine, clasped me
around the waist, and said that henceforth we were married, meaning in
his country's phrase that we were bosom friends. He would gladly die for me, if
the need should be. In a countryman, this sudden flame of friendship would
have seemed far too premature, a thing to be much distrusted. But in this
simple savage, those old rules would not apply. After supper, and another social
chat and smoke, we went to our room together. He made me a present of his
imbalmed head, took out his enormous tobacco wallet, and groping under the
tobacco, drew out some $30 in silver.
then spreading them on the table and mechanically dividing them into two
equal portions, pushed one of them toward me and said it was mine. I was
going to remmonstrate, but he silenced me by pouring them into my trousers
pockets. I let them stay. He then went about his evening prayers, took out his
idol, and removed the paper fireboard.
By certain signs and symptoms, I thought he seemed anxious for me to join him.
But well, knowing what was to follow, I deliberated a moment whether in case he
invited me, I would comply, or otherwise.
I was a good Christian, born and bred in the bosom of the infallible Presbyterian
Church. How then could I unite with this wild idoltor in worshiping his piece of
wood? But what is worship? Thought I. Do you suppose now, Ishmael, that the
magnanimous God of heaven and earth, pagans and all included, can possibly be
jealous of an insignificant bit of black wood? Impossible. But what is worship?
To do the will of God. That is worship.
And what is the will of God? To do to my
fellow man what I would have my fellow man do to me. That is the will of God.
Now Quiquake is my fellow man. And what do I wish that this qui quue would do to
me? Why unite with me in my particular Presbyterian form of worship?
Consequently, I must then unite with him in his ergo I must turn idoltor. So I
kindled the shavings, helped prop up the innocent little idol, offered him burnt
biscuit with queue, salammed before him twice or thrice, kissed his nose, and
that done. We undressed and went to bed at peace with our own consciences and
all the world. But we did not go to sleep without some little chat. How it
is, I know not, but there is no place like a bed for confidential disclosures
between friends. Men and wife, they say, there open the very bottom of their
souls to each other, and some old couples often lie and chat over old
times till nearly morning. Thus then, in our hearts honeymoon, lay I in Que, a
cozy, loving pair.